<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<!--A DOCTYPE declaration declaring a DTD is not need for DocBook 5.x, which uses RelaxNG and Schematron instead. 
    It is used here as a container for entity declarations.-->

<!DOCTYPE chapter 
[
    <!ENTITY % shared-content SYSTEM "shared-content.ent">
    %shared-content;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1" xml:id="introduction">
    <title xml:id="introduction.title">Introduction</title>
    <para/>
    <para><link xlink:href="https://katzenpost.network/blog/2024-04-12-hpqc/"/></para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">"hpqc - hybrid post quantum cryptography library"</emphasis></para>
    <para>(and other things in this blog)</para>
    <para/>
    <para>• Why is this the right tool for me? • Most advanced (PD hybrid) crypto, best anonymity,
        best mixnet protocols. </para>
    <para>• The Noise Protocol Framework is used end to end in KP., in place of TLS. Too much tech
        debt. Much simpler and better integrated overlay network. </para>
    <para>• Threat model document has a one page summeary – use it in the admin guide. Currently in
        blogpost section. </para>
    <para>Router defniton: creates ingress and egress queues. KP adds of crytptographui between.
        Ques with thread pools in between, capable of dynamically dropping packets based. </para>
    <para>Client2 – description of the protocol should be drawn from the paper. Minimal history
        about advancements over Loopix.<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>There are old and new protocols. Katzen currently supports only the old
                    protocol. What is this referring to? Loopix is the old protocol. Poor anonymity
                    because direct connections are observable. Typical of the disconnect between
                    academic s and the real world desired features. The choose the wrong threat
                    model. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The new protocol has durable streams</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
        
                <para>OLD</para>
                <para>Katzenpost can be used as a message oriented transport for a variety of
                    applications and is in no way limited to the e-mail use case demonstrated by the
                        <code>mailproxy</code> client/library. Other possible applications of
                    Katzenpost include but are not limited to: instant messenger applications,
                    crypto currency transaction transport, bulletin board systems, file sharing and
                    so forth.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Insert somewhere:</emphasis></para>
    <para>
        <link
                    xlink:href="https://bench.cr.yp.to:41867/research/pl/mjgbpzht4pdympsqbcmfudcxoe"
                    xml:id="RHS_ROOT_time_mjgbpzht4pdympsqbcmfudcxoe">1:56
                    PM</link></para>
    <para>
       @jdormansteele we should mention somewhere in the server side
                    documentation that ALL katzenpost mixnets have packet loss during startup
                    because mix nodes accept connections before they've connected outbound, so when
                    they receive packets they get dropped since there is nowhere to send
                    them.</para>


    <para><emphasis role="bold">*** Mine the academic paper ***</emphasis></para>
   

                
</chapter>
