<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article>
<article
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
  <info>
    <title>Sphinx Packet Replay Detection</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>David</firstname>
          <surname>Stainton</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </info>
  <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Abstract</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
    This document defines the replay detection for any protocol that
    uses Sphinx cryptographic packet format. This document is meant to
    serve as an implementation guide and document the existing replay
    protect for deployed mix networks.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="introduction">
    <title>1. Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The Sphinx cryptographic packet format is a compact and provably
      secure design introduced by George Danezis and Ian Goldberg
      <link linkend="SPHINX09">SPHINX09</link>. Although it supports
      replay detection, the exact mechanism of replay detection is
      neither described in <link linkend="SPHINX09">SPHINX09</link> nor
      is it described in our
      <link linkend="SPHINXSPEC">SPHINXSPEC</link>. Therefore we shall
      describe in detail how to efficiently detect Sphinx packet replay
      attacks.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="terminology">
      <title>1.1 Terminology</title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>Epoch</literal> - A fixed time interval defined in
            section <quote>4.2 Sphinx Mix and Provider Key
            Rotation</quote> of
            <link linkend="KATZMIXNET">KATZMIXNET</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>Packet</literal> - A fixed-length sequence of bytes
            transmitted through the network, containing the encrypted
            message and metadata for routing.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>Header</literal> - The packet header consisting of
            several components, which convey the information necessary
            to verify packet integrity and correctly process the packet.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>Payload</literal> - The fixed-length portion of a
            packet containing an encrypted message or part of a message,
            to be delivered.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>Group</literal> - A finite set of elements and a
            binary operation that satisfy the properties of closure,
            associativity, invertability, and the presence of an
            identity element.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>Group element</literal> - An individual element of
            the group.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>Group generator</literal> - A group element capable
            of generating any other element of the group, via repeated
            applications of the generator and the group operation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <literal>SEDA</literal> - Staged Event Driven Architecture.
        <link linkend="SEDA">SEDA</link> 1. A highly parallelizable
        computation model. 2. A computational pipeline composed of
        multiple stages connected by queues utilizing active queue
        management algorithms that can evict items from the queue based
        on dwell time or other criteria where each stage is a thread
        pool. 3. The only correct way to efficiently implement a
        software based router on general purpose computing hardware.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="conventions-used-in-this-document">
      <title>1.2 Conventions Used in This Document</title>
      <para>
        The key words <quote>MUST</quote>, <quote>MUST NOT</quote>,
        <quote>REQUIRED</quote>, <quote>SHALL</quote>, <quote>SHALL
        NOT</quote>, <quote>SHOULD</quote>, <quote>SHOULD NOT</quote>,
        <quote>RECOMMENDED</quote>, <quote>MAY</quote>, and
        <quote>OPTIONAL</quote> in this document are to be interpreted
        as described in <link linkend="RFC2119">RFC2119</link>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sphinx-cryptographic-primitives">
    <title>2. Sphinx Cryptographic Primitives</title>
    <para>
      This specification borrows the following cryptographic primitives
      constants from our <link linkend="SPHINXSPEC">SPHINXSPEC</link>:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>H(M)</literal> - A cryptographic hash function which
          takes an byte array M to produce a digest consisting of a
          <literal>HASH_LENGTH</literal> byte array.
          <literal>H(M)</literal> MUST be pre-image and collision
          resistant.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>EXP(X, Y)</literal> - An exponentiation function
          which takes the <literal>GROUP_ELEMENT_LENGTH</literal> byte
          array group elements <literal>X</literal> and
          <literal>Y</literal>, and returns <literal>X ^^ Y</literal> as
          a <literal>GROUP_ELEMENT_LENGTH</literal> byte array.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Let <literal>G</literal> denote the generator of the group, and
      <literal>EXP_KEYGEN()</literal> return a
      <literal>GROUP_ELEMENT_LENGTH</literal> byte array group element
      usable as private key.
    </para>
    <para>
      The group defined by <literal>G</literal> and
      <literal>EXP(X, Y)</literal> MUST satisfy the Decision
      Diffie-Hellman problem.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="sphinx-parameter-constants">
      <title>2.1 Sphinx Parameter Constants</title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>HASH_LENGTH</literal> - 32 bytes. Katzenpost
            currently uses SHA-512/256.
            <link linkend="RFC6234">RFC6234</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>GROUP_ELEMENT_LENGTH</literal> - 32 bytes.
            Katzenpost currently uses X25519.
            <link linkend="RFC7748">RFC7748</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="system-overview">
    <title>3. System Overview</title>
    <para>
      Mixes as currently deployed, have two modes of operation:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Sphinx routing keys and replay caches are persisted to disk
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Sphinx routing keys and replay caches are persisted to memory
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      These two modes of operation fundamentally represent a tradeoff
      between mix server availability and notional compulsion attack
      resistance. Ultimately it will be the mix operator’s decision to
      make since they affect the security and availability of their mix
      servers. In particular since mix networks are vulnerable to the
      various types of compulsion attacks (see
      <link linkend="SPHINXSPEC">SPHINXSPEC</link> section 9.4
      Compulsion Threat Considerations) and therefore there is some
      advantage to NOT persisting the Sphinx routing keys to disk. The
      mix operator can simply poweroff the mix server before seizure
      rather than physically destroying the disk in order to prevent
      capture of the Sphinx routing keys. An argument can be made for
      the use of full disk encryption, however this may not be practical
      for servers hosted in remote locations.
    </para>
    <para>
      On the other hand, persisting Sphinx routing keys and replay
      caches to disk is useful because it allows mix operators to
      shutdown their mix server for maintenance purposes without loosing
      these Sphinx routing keys and replay caches. This means that as
      soon as the maintenance operation is completed the mix server is
      able to rejoin the network. Our current PKI system
      <link linkend="KATZMIXPKI">KATZMIXPKI</link> does NOT provide a
      mechanism to notify Directory Authorities of such an outage or
      maintenance period. Therefore if there is loss of Sphinx routing
      keys this results in a mix outage until the next epoch.
    </para>
    <para>
      The two modes of operation both completely prevent replay attacks
      after a system restart. In the case of the disk persistence,
      replay attacks are prevented because all packets traversing the
      mix have their replay tags persisted to disk cache. This cache is
      therefore once again used to prevent replays after a system
      restart. In the case of memory persistence replays are prevented
      upon restart because the Sphinx routing keys are destroyed and
      therefore the mix will not participant in the network until at
      least the next epoch rotation. However availability of the mix may
      require two epoch rotations because in accordance with
      <link linkend="KATZMIXPKI">KATZMIXPKI</link> mixes publish future
      epoch keys so that Sphinx packets flowing through the network can
      seamlessly straddle the epoch boundaries.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sphinx-packet-replay-cache">
    <title>4. Sphinx Packet Replay Cache</title>
    <section xml:id="sphinx-replay-tag-composition">
      <title>4.1 Sphinx Replay Tag Composition</title>
      <para>
        The following excerpt from our
        <link linkend="SPHINXSPEC">SPHINXSPEC</link> shows how the
        replay tag is calculated.
      </para>
      <programlisting>
hdr = sphinx_packet.header
shared_secret = EXP( hdr.group_element, private_routing_key )
replay_tag = H( shared_secret )
</programlisting>
      <para>
        However this tag is not utilized in replay detection until the
        rest of the Sphinx packet is fully processed and it’s header MAC
        verified as described in
        <link linkend="SPHINXSPEC">SPHINXSPEC</link>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sphinx-replay-tag-caching">
    <title>4.2 Sphinx Replay Tag Caching</title>
    <para>
      It would be sufficient to use a key value store or hashmap to
      detect the presence of a duplicate replay tag however we
      additionaly employ a bloom filter to increase performance. Sphinx
      keys must periodically be rotated and destroyed to mitigate
      compulsion attacks and therefore our replay caches must likewise
      be rotated. This kind of key erasure scheme limits the window of
      time that an adversary can perform a compulsion attack. See our
      PKI specification <link linkend="KATZMIXPKI">KATZMIXPKI</link> for
      more details regarding epoch key rotation and the grace period
      before and after the epoch boundary.
    </para>
    <para>
      We tune our bloom filter for line-speed; that is to say the bloom
      filter for a given replay cache is tuned for the maximum number of
      Sphinx packets that can be sent on the wire during the epoch
      duration of the Sphinx routing key. This of course has to take
      into account the size of the Sphinx packets as well as the maximum
      line speed of the network interface. This is a conservative tuning
      heuristic given that there must be more than this maximum number
      of Sphinx packets in order for there to be duplicate packets.
    </para>
    <para>
      Our bloomfilter with hashmap replay detection cache looks like
      this:
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>replay cache</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="diagrams/replay1.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>replay cache</phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Note that this diagram does NOT express the full complexity of the
      replay caching system. In particular it does not describe how
      entries are entered into the bloom filter and hashmap. Upon either
      bloom filter mismatch or hashmap mismatch both data structures
      must be locked and the replay tag inserted into each.
    </para>
    <para>
      For the disk persistence mode of operation the hashmap can simply
      be replaced with an efficient key value store. Persistent stores
      may use a write back cache and other techniques for efficiency.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="epoch-boundaries">
      <title>4.3 Epoch Boundaries</title>
      <para>
        Since mixes publish future epoch keys (see
        <link linkend="KATZMIXPKI">KATZMIXPKI</link>) so that Sphinx
        packets flowing through the network can seamlessly straddle the
        epoch boundaries, our replay detection forms a special kind of
        double bloom filter system. During the epoch grace period mixes
        perform trial decryption of Sphinx packets. The replay cache
        used will be the one that is associated with the Sphinx routing
        key which was successfully used to decrypt (unwrap transform)
        the Sphinx packet. This is not a double bloom filter in the
        normal sense of this term since each bloom filter used is
        distinct and associated with it’s own cache, furthermore, replay
        tags are only ever inserted into one cache and one bloom filter.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="cost-of-checking-replays">
      <title>4.4 Cost Of Checking Replays</title>
      <para>
        The cost of checking a replay tag from a single replay cache is
        the sum of the following operations:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sphinx packet unwrap operation
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A bloom filter lookup
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A hashmap or cache lookup
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        Therefore these operations are roughly O(1) in complexity.
        However Sphinx packets processed near epoch boundaries will not
        be constant time due to trial decryption with two Sphinx routing
        keys as mentioned above in section <quote>3.3 Epoch
        Boundaries</quote>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="concurrent-processing-of-sphinx-packet-replay-tags">
    <title>5. Concurrent Processing of Sphinx Packet Replay Tags</title>
    <para>
      The best way to implement a software based router is with a
      <link linkend="SEDA">SEDA</link> computational pipeline. We
      therefore need a mechanism to allow multiple threads to reference
      our rotating Sphinx keys and associated replay caches. Here we
      shall describe a shadow memory system which the mix server uses
      such that the individual worker threads shall always have a
      reference to the current set of candidate mix keys and associates
      replay caches.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="pki-updates">
      <title>5.1 PKI Updates</title>
      <para>
        The mix server periodically updates it’s knowledge of the
        network by downloading a new consensus document as described in
        <link linkend="KATZMIXPKI">KATZMIXPKI</link>. The individual
        threads in the <quote>cryptoworker</quote> thread pool which
        process Sphinx packets make use of a <literal>MixKey</literal>
        data structure which consists of:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sphinx routing key material (public and private X25519 keys)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Replay Cache
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Reference Counter
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        Each of these <quote>cryptoworker</quote> thread pool has it’s
        own hashmap associating epochs to a reference to the
        <literal>MixKey</literal>. The mix server PKI threat maintains a
        single hashmap which associates the epochs with the
        corresponding <literal>MixKey</literal>. We shall refer to this
        hashmap as <literal>MixKeys</literal>. After a new
        <literal>MixKey</literal> is added to
        <literal>MixKeys</literal>, a <quote>reshadow</quote> operation
        is performed for each <quote>cryptoworker</quote> thread. The
        <quote>reshadow</quote> operation performs two tasks:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Removes entries from each <quote>cryptoworker</quote>
            thread's hashmap that are no longer present in
            <literal>MixKeys</literal> and decrements the
            <literal>MixKey</literal> reference counter.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Adds entries present in <literal>MixKeys</literal> but are
            not present in the thread’s hashmap and increments the
            <literal>MixKey</literal> reference counter.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        Once a given <literal>MixKey</literal> reference counter is
        decremented to zero, the <literal>MixKey</literal> and it’s
        associated on disk data is purged. Note that we do not discuss
        synchronization primitives, however it should be obvious that
        updating the replay cache should likely make use of a mutex or
        similar primitive to avoid data races between
        <quote>cryptoworker</quote> threads.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="appendix-a.-references">
    <title>Appendix A. References</title>
    <section xml:id="appendix-a.1-normative-references">
      <title>Appendix A.1 Normative References</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix-a.2-informative-references">
      <title>Appendix A.2 Informative References</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="appendix-b.-citing-this-document">
    <title>Appendix B. Citing This Document</title>
    <section xml:id="appendix-b.1-bibtex-entry">
      <title>Appendix B.1 Bibtex Entry</title>
      <para>
        Note that the following bibtex entry is in the IEEEtran bibtex
        style as described in a document called <quote>How to Use the
        IEEEtran BIBTEX Style</quote>.
      </para>
      <programlisting>
@online{SphinxReplay,
title = {Sphinx Packet Replay Detection Specification},
author = {David Stainton},
url = {https://github.com/katzenpost/katzenpost/blob/main/docs/specs/sphinx_replay_detection.rst},
year = {2019}
}
</programlisting>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">COMPULS05</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Danezis, G., Clulow, J., <quote>Compulsion Resistant Anonymous
        Communications</quote>, Proceedings of Information Hiding
        Workshop, June 2005,
        https://www.freehaven.net/anonbib/cache/ih05-danezisclulow.pdf
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">KATZMIXNET</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Angel, Y., Danezis, G., Diaz, C., Piotrowska, A., Stainton, D.,
        <quote>Katzenpost Mix Network Specification</quote>, June 2017,
        https://github.com/katzenpost/katzenpost/blob/main/docs/specs/mixnet.md
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">KATZMIXPKI</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Angel, Y., Piotrowska, A., Stainton, D., <quote>Katzenpost Mix
        Network Public Key Infrastructure Specification</quote>,
        December 2017,
        https://github.com/katzenpost/katzenpost/blob/main/docs/specs/pki.md
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">RFC2119</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Bradner, S., <quote>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
        Requirement Levels</quote>, BCP 14, RFC 2119, DOI
        10.17487/RFC2119, March 1997,
        http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">RFC6234</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Eastlake 3rd, D. and T. Hansen, <quote>US Secure Hash Algorithms
        (SHA and SHA-based HMAC and HKDF)</quote>, RFC 6234, DOI
        10.17487/RFC6234, May 2011,
        https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6234
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">RFC7748</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Langley, A., Hamburg, M., and S. Turner, <quote>Elliptic Curves
        for Security</quote>, RFC 7748, January 2016.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">SEDA</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Welsh, M., Culler, D., Brewer, E., <quote>SEDA: An Architecture
        for Well-Conditioned, Scalable Internet Services</quote>, ACM
        Symposium on Operating Systems Principles, 2001,
        http://www.sosp.org/2001/papers/welsh.pdf
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">SPHINX09</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Danezis, G., Goldberg, I., <quote>Sphinx: A Compact and Provably
        Secure Mix Format</quote>, DOI 10.1109/SP.2009.15, May 2009,
        https://cypherpunks.ca/~iang/pubs/Sphinx_Oakland09.pdf
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">SPHINXSPEC</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        Angel, Y., Danezis, G., Diaz, C., Piotrowska, A., Stainton, D.,
        <quote>Sphinx Mix Network Cryptographic Packet Format
        Specification</quote> July 2017,
        https://github.com/katzenpost/katzenpost/blob/main/docs/specs/sphinx.md
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
